<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Union pursued, in a letter to Mr. Baxter, concerning his late book of national churches published for a fuller disquisition about this subject, by the sober and composed of all sides, in order to comprehension which hath been forming, and a larger constitution of the church to be formed, when that Day of Concord comes, which the gentle aspect of Heaven in God's appointment (and the King's) of so many choice moderate bishops together at this time does presage to the nation, that the Presbyterians and Independants, that have united within themselves, may both be united also with the Church of England / by a lover of Him, and follower of peace.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15748</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11849608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11849608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 498:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Union pursued, in a letter to Mr. Baxter, concerning his late book of national churches published for a fuller disquisition about this subject, by the sober and composed of all sides, in order to comprehension which hath been forming, and a larger constitution of the church to be formed, when that Day of Concord comes, which the gentle aspect of Heaven in God's appointment (and the King's) of so many choice moderate bishops together at this time does presage to the nation, that the Presbyterians and Independants, that have united within themselves, may both be united also with the Church of England / by a lover of Him, and follower of peace.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Of national churches.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  Anglican Communion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49900:1"/>
            <p>Union Purſued; IN A Letter to Mr. Baxter, Concerning his Late Book of <hi>National Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PUBLISHED For a fuller Diſquiſition about this Subject, by the Sober and Compoſed of all Sides, in order to <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> which hath been Forming, and a <hi>Larger Conſtitution of the Church</hi> to be Formed, when that Day of Concord comes, which the gentle Aſpect of Heaven in GOD's Appointment (and the <hi>King</hi>'s) of ſo many Choice Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Biſhops together at this Time does preſage to the Nation.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independants,</hi> that have United within themſelves, may Both be United alſo with the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Lover of Him, and Follower of Peace.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Baldwin,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49900:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49900:2"/>
            <head>A Letter to Mr. Baxter, Concerning his Late BOOK of National Churches.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving read your Sheets of <hi>National Churches,</hi> which Subject I am much pleaſed with, and concern'd, in Regard to the Publick: I cannot but deſire you, who have a more diſtinct Knowledge of theſe things than I, to endeavour to clear to me this Matter a little farther than you have.</p>
            <p>Your Notion of a <hi>National Church</hi> to be all one with a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kingdom,</hi> and to be of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> is <hi>New</hi> as I take it. That it is the Duty of Nations, Magiſtrate and People, to become Chriſtians, and that King and People ſhould meet in fit Aſſemblies for the Worſhip of the True God and His Son, and live as Chriſtians, there is no body can doubt: But that all ſuch Particular Congregations ſhould combine into one Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or be Unified in a <hi>National Church;</hi> this is, as I think, another Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>There are two things belong to a <hi>Polity,</hi> the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> and the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi> A Polity muſt be firſt Conſtituted, that is, <hi>An Order of Superiority and Subjection</hi> agreed upon <hi>by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity,</hi> (which implies a Union for Government) before it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49900:3"/>be Governed according to <hi>that Order,</hi> which is the <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> A <hi>Community</hi> is (with Politick Writers) but the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed</hi> for the receiving a <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom turn'd Chriſtian, (Head and Body) are in the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Conſideration no other than a <hi>Community.</hi> There muſt be a <hi>Conſtitution</hi> then <hi>made</hi> by that <hi>Community,</hi> a Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution agreed upon by Magiſtrate and People for the Common Good, before they be a <hi>National Church.</hi> The <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> are always diſtinguiſhed, and the placing the Supreme Power of a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in a <hi>King,</hi> or in the <hi>Nobles,</hi> or in the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> or in a Government that is <hi>Mixt,</hi> does not ſpecifie the Conſtitution of the <hi>Church.</hi> The Supreme Legiſlative and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Power of the <hi>One</hi> and the <hi>Other,</hi> does not lye in the ſame <hi>Subject.</hi> I pray conſider if it do; if it does, then muſt a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kingdom</hi> and <hi>National Church</hi> be the ſame indeed; but if it do not, then muſt it be <hi>otherwiſe</hi> according to the beſt of my Apprehenſion, which I deſire to be rectified where it is amiſs, and ſhall not therefore enlarge, and be petulant on this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>You ſeem to place the Being of a <hi>National Church</hi> onely in the having a King and People to be Chriſtian, but I am apt to place it mainly (as to the Polity thereof) in that Combination of King and People in ſuch an Order as is conducive to the Exerciſe of a <hi>Government Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> which is proper to it; which Order of Superiority and Inferiority, being diverſe in diverſe Nations, cannot be of Divine Appointment, becauſe the Polity then ought to be the ſame in every Country. That which is of <hi>God</hi>'s Appointment, cannot be varyed by <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am of the Opinion, That in <hi>Scotland</hi> they may do well in ſetting up the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government, and in <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> and both Nations do for the beſt. Both be True <hi>National Churches,</hi> and acceptable to Chriſt. Now I cannot tell how to make ſo much Charity good, but by reckoning that <hi>Polity</hi> which is set up in Churches as <hi>National,</hi> to be left to the Liberty of Chriſtian Governours, and conſequently to be of <hi>Human Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Nation ſhould be converted to Chriſtianity by ſome <hi>Independents,</hi> and they ſet up their Independent Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches throughout the Land without other Government: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49900:3"/>the King be of the ſame mind, and ſo joyns himſelf to one of theſe Congregations, as a Member, and believes that he is to leave all Eccleſiaſtical Government to ſuch Paſtors, and meddle not with it: I ask you, whether ſuch a Kingdom be a National Church, or a National Eccleſiaſtical Polity, where there is no Order of Superiority and Inferiority for the exerciſe of any Government proper to it?</p>
            <p>I ask, Whether the very <hi>Quod ſit,</hi> or that there ought to be a Political National Government in every ſuch Kingdom, by vertue of any Precept or Inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt, can be made good? It is, I ſay, a Queſtion, at leaſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>Independents,</hi> Whether every King and People are bound to combine and agree upon the ſetting up any Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eccleſiaſtical Government at all, but rather leave the People to their particular Congregations and Paſtors, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on any Higher Power, for any other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Government of Man, over them than that. Does the Scripture require farther than this?</p>
            <p>I ask on, Suppoſe the <hi>Quod ſit,</hi> What ſhall we do about the <hi>Quid ſit?</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> are for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for the <hi>Epiſcopal;</hi> I cannot abide you ſhould condemn either: How will you allow both, but by making a National Conſtitution indifferent? And how can it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, if it were not of Human Agreement? What may be granted to the one, and what to the other, and yet Chriſt's Command of National Churches (if there be any) be not tranſgreſſed, I muſt ask you as an harder Task.</p>
            <p>Again, I muſt ask you about the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church. This is either <hi>Myſtical,</hi> the Government whereof is only <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> and I have no Queſtion to ask about that: Or <hi>Viſible</hi> (as they call it) the Government whereof is <hi>External.</hi> The Catholick Church Viſible conſiſts of Chriſt, as the Head, and all Profeſſors, as the Body: Theſe Profeſſors make up Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregations; theſe Congregations, or their Paſtors, being confederated into Claſſes, or under Dioceſans, till they come to a general Aſſembly, or a Convocation, ariſe into a National Church, independent on any foreign Juriſdiction. Now I muſt ask, That foraſmuch as all the Churches on Earth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49900:4"/>cannot be combined under any General Officers for the exerciſe of an <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Government, whether the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church on Earth be a Church <hi>Political?</hi> That is, Foraſmuch as there is no Confederation of Churches <hi>National,</hi> as there is, or may be of <hi>Parochial, Dioceſan,</hi> and <hi>Provincial,</hi> for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon which account you do readily diſown a <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>General Council;</hi> I ask, How can you make out a Polity <hi>Oecumenical?</hi> I know you ſay it is a Church <hi>Political,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Body?</hi> But, How can any Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Polity, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, be poſſible to Man? Can a Society be <hi>Political</hi> before it be <hi>Organical?</hi> And, Can the Catholick Church be ſo, being even quite unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any Catholick Officers, for executing ſuch Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction?</p>
            <p>You ſay, the Head gives the Form to a Society; but, Does it give the Form when there are no Organs or Officers for Government under that Head, when there are no ſuch appointed by him, or can be made by Man? It is true, that the actual making Officers belongs to the <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a Government, when the Government hath its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, and is Organical from the <hi>Conſtitution:</hi> But, where is there any ſuch Conſtitution declared by Chriſt, or Appointment of his, that there ſhould be Organs made for an <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Government? If there be no ſuch, how is it a Polity without Government, without virtual or actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Government; or an Oecumenical Polity without an Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menical Government? This would tempt a man to come about towards our firſt Doctrin of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to deny any Church-<hi>Catholick</hi> but the <hi>Inviſible.</hi> How can the Univerſal <hi>Coetus</hi> of Chriſtian People, diſperſed through the World without <hi>Legiſlative</hi> or <hi>Judicial</hi> Power be <hi>Political?</hi> Methinks there muſt be ſomething elſe more than Head and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers eſſential to a <hi>Form</hi> of Polity, whether Civil or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical?</p>
            <p>I will tell you therefore over again the Opinion I am prone to, as well as I can. A National Church may be conſidered <hi>Materially</hi> as a Chriſtian People or Kingdom, and ſo are National Churches of Chriſt's appointment out of doubt (as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49900:4"/>at the beginning acknowledged) for He ſent out his Officers to convert <hi>Nations</hi> rather than <hi>ſingle Men;</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> have many Places of the calling of Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, whoſe Anſwer to that Call makes them Churches: But as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church is conſidered <hi>Formally</hi> in regard to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of divers particular Countries, as we ſay the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the like, a National Church is, and muſt be, (as it ſeems to me) of Human A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement altogether.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this (I muſt farther ſay) to diſpute with you, but to learn of you, or for Inſtruction; and in making this out, I cannot but, in my native apprehenſion, differ from y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ou as to that which gives the Form, Being, or Eſſence to a Society Political; or, as to that which is the <hi>ratio forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> of a Nation, being a Church. You ſay, it is only the Head gives the Form; but I apprehend, That the Head and Members of any Society, conſidered as in a ſtate before Organization for Regiment, are but ſtill the <hi>Matter</hi> of a Polity; but that which gives the <hi>Form</hi> to it, is Conſent. If a Community, (let me ſay) ſhould agree upon a Head, and not agree upon the Organizing that Head and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſo as to be capable of Government, here is no Polity. Let me ſpeak cloſer; When a King is Head of his People already, as They are a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> I cannot ſay he is a Head of them as a <hi>Church,</hi> before this Church be made <hi>Organical</hi> by a <hi>Constitution.</hi> Pray note that, and I ſay then, The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Agreement, or Combination of the Community; the <hi>Populus,</hi> Head and Body, in ſuch an Order for Government as is proper to it, is the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> in my Apprehenſion of that Society.</p>
            <p>I know, that the Terms of <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> (upon which I lay no ſtreſs) are proper to <hi>phyſical</hi> Beings; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a <hi>Polity,</hi> and ſuch-like things, are not <hi>Entia phyſica,</hi> nor <hi>Entia rationis,</hi> but <hi>Entia moralia,</hi> and ſo need other Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but when I have no better, and <hi>Entia moralia ad ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiam phyſicorum concipiuntur,</hi> I muſt ſay, That as it is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> that makes a ſingle man a Member of a Society, and does that which a <hi>Form</hi> does, to wit, give the <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49900:5"/>to him of a Member <hi>(Forma dat eſſe &amp; nomen):</hi> So muſt the Univerſal Conſent of Parts, to that Order of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Inferiority for Regiment, which is in any Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, give it its <hi>Form,</hi> and that <hi>Order</hi> be the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Polity</hi> it ſelf, which conſiſting not only of Head and Members, but of Head and ſubordinate Organs for that Regiment, it is not the Head alone, but Head and Body ſo organized (the Head Principally indeed, but Jointly) that makes it a Political So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
            <p>You may ſay, that I write here but ſcatteredly, as one that aims at ſaying ſomething that may provoke you to ſet me right, rather than come my ſelf to any perfect Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; and I care not to have you think and judge ſo; for, though I would not put you to trouble willingly about any thing impertinent, yet do I expect ſo much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and farther light from you in the thing, as the weight of the Subject, and the concernment thereof, does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him that undertook it.</p>
            <p>The Head gives the Form, I expreſs, as your Judgment. In <hi>one</hi> place of this Book, or that which came out with it, you ſay <hi>The Head is the Form;</hi> which ſeems to me <hi>abſonant;</hi> In another place, you ſay, The Relative Union between the Head and Body, or the <hi>pars imporans &amp; ſubdita</hi> is the Form, which ſounds well: But the Conception is not ſo hard yet, <hi>A Polity is an Order of Superiority</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> (I have ſaid) <hi>in a Community.</hi> The <hi>Community</hi> here is the <hi>Matter,</hi> and this <hi>Order</hi> is the <hi>Form.</hi> This is moſt plain; and foraſmuch as this Form is introduc'd into the Community by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, while free, it is Conſent which gives the Form, and is the Foundation (the <hi>Fundamentum Relationis</hi>) of all Societies.</p>
            <p>And here, Sir, without interpoſition of the laſt Paragraph, I though to break off, but my Mind, I feel, is not emptied. <hi>A Chriſtian Kingdom, containing Confederate Paſtoral Churches, is a National Church</hi> with you: But, what if there be no <hi>Confederacy,</hi> no ſuch Conſent or National Confederacy? Where is the Form that muſt give the Being and Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49900:5"/>of a National Church to ſuch a Kingdom? Suppoſe a Company of Chriſtians with Miniſters among them, who preach and pray together, and yet are not <hi>Confederated</hi> in the Choice of any of them for a Paſtor, and Officers for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Here is a Particular Worſhipping Community, but no Political Society: So in a Kingdom, if a King and People be Chriſtian, and they have Particular Churches, but no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of theſe Churches or Paſtors, in an Order for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Government, here is an Eccleſiaſtical National <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> but no National <hi>Church:</hi> Here is a Government which is Civil by the <hi>Sword,</hi> but no Government Eccleſiaſtical by the <hi>Keys.</hi> There can be no <hi>Keys</hi> that are <hi>National</hi> I muſt ſay, but what are founded in this <hi>Confederacy,</hi> and conſequently on <hi>Human Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may ſay, every King that is Chriſtian, may allow of what Particular Churches he pleaſe, and command a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy: But hold a little, Religion (the Fathers and Reaſon will tell us) cannot be forced. The <hi>Church, Man</hi> believes <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government to be <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> thinks <hi>his</hi> to be ſo; the <hi>Independent</hi> thinks <hi>their</hi> Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Churches alone to be of Chriſts Appointment, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in Conſcience ſubmit to a Confederacy of the one Side or the other: How ſhall the King here command Conſent or Confederacy to any one part, againſt the Conſcience of the other? Thou ſhalt do nothing againſt thy Conſcience, is a Precept of God and Nature, that binds <hi>ſemper &amp; ad ſemper</hi> (as the Schools ſpeak) being Negative: How then ſhall <hi>Man</hi> command what GOD forbids? He commands you to Confederate, and it is againſt you Conſcience to do it. Hath he Power to command a Subject to ſin? He hath Strength, or Force, or Legal Right, but hath he Authority to do it? To ſay how far the Supreme Majeſtrate may go in this Caſe, is not eaſie. I am ſure a Man may eaſily be too haſty and ſudden in ſuch a Deciſion.</p>
            <p>I muſt add, as what appears from that which went before; A <hi>National Church</hi> may be diſtinguiſhed from a <hi>Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> becauſe a People may be Chriſtian before ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy: But when Confederated, and a Church, they are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49900:6"/>the ſame indeed, ſo, as though <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> they cannot be <hi>divided.</hi> And this is the Right in my Apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>To talk of <hi>Diſſenters, Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> to be Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as well as the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> will not be born by the <hi>Weak:</hi> And the confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Government with the <hi>Civil,</hi> which your making a Kingdom and Church as Chriſtian to be the ſame, does ſeem to do, will by the <hi>Wiſe</hi> be called into Queſtion. When you ſay well, or ſpeak at beſt, you muſt look for Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding and Clamour from the Diſpleaſed.</p>
            <p>For my own part, how the Church <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> whereof <hi>Christ</hi> is the <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Particular</hi> Churches, whereof the <hi>Paſtors</hi> have Rule, are Churches of Chriſts making, I do underſtand: But how far a <hi>National</hi> Church is of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s making, and how far of <hi>Mans</hi> making, I think requires a little more Explication from you, than we have yet. You are very exact as to <hi>Civil</hi> Government, to tell us what is of <hi>GOD,</hi> and what of <hi>Man:</hi> I remember not that you are ſo full as to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let me tell you, leſt I be miſtaken as to thoſe things I have asked before, that I have done ſo, not that I am in all of them of another mind from you, but for the clearing my leſs perſpicacious Conceptions. For Inſtance, when I ask, Whether the Catholick Church Viſible be Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical? I muſt ſay I have receiv'd it to be ſo, and will give you my Account, that you may tell me if I am ſhort. The Government of the Church Myſtical, which is <hi>Internal</hi> by God's Spirit, is (I count) a Government, over ſingle Perſons (the <hi>Elect diſperſed</hi>); His Operation is on ſingle Perſons: The Government of the Church Viſible, which is <hi>External,</hi> is a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Churches, a Government of Perſons as in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, Congregational, Dioceſan, Provincial, National. And the Catholick Church Viſible, is a Church (I count) <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> and <hi>Organical,</hi> becauſe all theſe Churches that are Parts of it, have their Governing Officers as well as the People Governed, contained in them. There is a Government there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of a Society, <hi>per Partes,</hi> or <hi>per Integrum.</hi> The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church is a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> and is Governed <hi>per Partes</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49900:6"/>only; but yet by the Univerſal Laws of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the Head of it alone, without any Oecumenical Vicarious <hi>Soveraign,</hi> Single or Collective under him, to give any other binding Laws than his; which both you and I equally decry. Whether there by any more than this to be Anſwered, is the end of my asking that Queſtion of you, from whom I count if there be, I ſhall have it.</p>
            <p>For the Caſe put by me of a Kingdom converted by <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> it is my Opinion, That, in a Kingdom conſiſting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Paſtoral Churches, not aſſociated into an Order of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority and Subjection for a Government of the <hi>Whole</hi> (or <hi>per Integrum</hi>) there can be only the <hi>Materia</hi> and <hi>Privatio,</hi> but not the <hi>Forma</hi> (which that Order introduced ſhould be) of a <hi>National Church.</hi> And I muſt add, If it be enough that a King and People be Chriſtian with Paſtoral Churches, to make a Kingdom a National Church, then ſuppoſing the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government comes to be ſet up in it, here muſt be tow National Churches in one Kingdom, for there was one before, and here is a New one, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther New conſtituted by Agreement. Pray pardon me my ſeeking from you more Illumination.</p>
            <p>For your Proof of National Churches to be of Chriſt's Inſtitution, from his own being King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Head of the National Church, and chooſing <hi>Twelve</hi> Apoſtles in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their <hi>Tribes,</hi> and <hi>Seventy</hi> other, in relation to their <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim,</hi> with the Particulars you further mention, I confeſs what you offer to be very ingenious, and deep in fancy, but whether it be cogent or not, I do queſtion. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Though Chriſt was born King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as ſprung from <hi>David</hi> by his Mother, yet would he not be their King, when the <hi>Jews</hi> would have made him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He tells expreſly, <hi>His Kingdom was not of this World:</hi> Whereas the Government of Kings over Chriſtian Kingdoms, and ſo Heads of National Churches, is no other than a Government <hi>External,</hi> or a Government <hi>which is of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirldy,</hi> Chriſt is every where ſaid in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> to be Head of his Church, in the Senſe of the Church Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49900:7"/>but never in the Senſe of the Particular Church of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation: And the Prophecies of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> will admit, if not require by the Event, another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Relation of the <hi>Seventy</hi> to the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and of the <hi>Twelve</hi> to the <hi>Tribes,</hi> is a Relation only of Number, not of Work or Office; for, What is the Seventy Diſciples preaching to convent the People, or preaching Repentance for remiſſion of ſins, to the buſineſs of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> which was their Supreme Court of Judicature, for all Cauſes to be brought for Judgment? And, what was that Nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of <hi>Twelve Tribes</hi> to the Choice of the <hi>Twelve Apoſtles,</hi> unleſs one might think, that Chriſt ſet over each Tribe one of them, to be Superintendent, or Biſhop of that Tribe, which none Thinks as I Know.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Though the <hi>Jews</hi> had their <hi>Twelve Tribes,</hi> and Chriſt thoſe <hi>Twelve Apoſtles,</hi> and they had <hi>Seventy</hi> Elders, and Chriſt choſe out Seventy to preach the Goſpel, this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies not, (beſides what is ſaid already) unleſs you prove theſe two things, which can't be proved; to wit, That he choſe theſe <hi>Twelve</hi> in relation to theſe <hi>Tribes,</hi> and theſe <hi>Seventy</hi> in relation to their <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> and, Who can tell Chriſt's Intention? And alſo, That he did this by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as their King, as King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> or Head of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, when he might do it (and did it, we may ſuppoſe) as King or Head of the Church <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal?</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if any ſhall ſay, that Chriſt, during his Life, was King only of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that he had no Power therefore of commiſſiouating his apoſtles to go any where elſe for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting People, which is the making them Subjects of his Kingdom, becauſe he was not King over any other Nation, till after his Death and Reſurrection; and ſhall then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this by the proving that it was at his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> he was inaugurated into his Univerſal Kingdom, or make King over the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or all Nations, as Heir of the World; That is was then, that God ſaid to him, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee;</hi> and Chriſt <hi>askt of</hi> his Father, and <hi>he gave him the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49900:7"/>ends of the Earth for his poſſeſſion</hi> (compare <hi>Acts</hi> 13.33, with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7, 8.); That it was then, and not before then, that he received <hi>all power in Heaven and Earth,</hi> (as he tells his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.) and by vertue of that Power, commiſſioned the Apoſtles to go and <hi>diſciple all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> If any can diſtinguiſh thus, There was a Kingdom Chriſt was <hi>Born</hi> to (<hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.37.) which is the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kingdom, as being of the Line of <hi>David.</hi> And there is a Kingdom which is <hi>Given</hi> him as the Son of Man, (<hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14.) and which was Purchaſed by the Merits of his Life and Death, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 24.26. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8.) and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently there muſt be a time when it was <hi>Received,</hi> and that muſt be after his Death and Reſurrection upon that Account. I ſay now, if any ſtand upon this, and it be Truth (which whether it be or no I muſt ſtill ask you) then is there the Acceſs of ſome Light and Strength to your Notion: But that Chriſt <hi>Inſtituted</hi> a National Church Form, and that <hi>Judaea</hi> under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was ſuch a Church in the <hi>Execution,</hi> which are Two Chapters of your Book, I do not apprehend the Proof ſo convincing, but that they need both of them your ſecond Thoughts, and farther Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement.</p>
            <p>That which affects me in theſe Papers more eſpecially, is this one thing, that you ſhew ſo much candour and conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention toward the preſent Church, but without fawning I muſt confeſs, and with no leſs ſerious Frame of Spirit (if I can judge) than <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wrote his <hi>Retractations.</hi> I do not know whether our <hi>Church-men,</hi> who are good, will refuſe you any thing you offer as pious, as prudent, or as neceſſary to Communion: And, I think you have offered and conceded enough to the laying a Ground for both Parties, when GOD and a Parliament ſhall ſee it good, to come to an Accommodation.</p>
            <p>I will give an Example of what I ſay to my Reader out of the Fourteenth <hi>Chap.</hi> of your Book, where you have theſe words. <hi>The National Church of</hi> England <hi>is rightly Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted under one ſupream Royal Government, as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49900:8"/>Head. It is duely Conſtituted of profeſſed Baptized Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Churches as the Subject Matter. It hath National Laws which profeſs their Subſerviency to the Law of Chriſt, and the Nullity of all that is againſt it. It maketh none Magiſtrates but profeſſed Chriſtians, no nor Burgeſſes, and Chooſers of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. It hath Dioceſans, that are general Overſeers of many particular Churches, as ſucceſſors to the Apostles and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, in the Ordinary parts, of their Office. It juſtly maketh Biſhops Members of Parliament, it being unfit to make Laws for Religion without the Pastors notice and advice. It juſtly giveth large maintenance, and honours to the Superior Clergy, that they may be a protection to the Inferior, and a relief to the poor, and keep up Religion from the contempt and ſcorn of Wordly Men. The King is the juſt Donor of ſuch Honours and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues. The Pariſh Miniſters according to the true Legal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church of</hi> England, <hi>are acknowledged true Paſtors, as to all the Eſſentials of the Paſtoral Office, Word, Sacraments, Keys, Diſcipline, and Ordinations. The Inferior Miniſters in Tythes and Glebe, have a laudable maintenance. All Pariſhes are to diſtinguiſh Communicating Members from Non communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Inhabitants, and to refuſe the ſcandalous and unconfirmed, not ready or deſiring Confirmation. And the Offices of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and Burial, are fitted to the faithful, were Diſcipline executed. Yet our Law for Diſſenters Aſſemblies, acknowledgeth them all true Members of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>who agree in the Eſſentials, notwithſtanding their diſſent in leſſer things. We uſe one and the ſame Tranſlation of Scripture, and we all renounce all Humane, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, Forreign Juriſdiction.</hi> Theſe things, and all theſe, you approve as commendable, and when you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede ſo much to the Biſhops, what is it you require of them? Why nothing, but that Reformation in effect only of ſome things, which, they themſelves, as to the main, do ſeek alſo; and what Ingenuity more than this, could be expected from any? It is <hi>Peace</hi> I perceive you would have, but <hi>Holineſs</hi> more; and when the world lyes in wickedneſs, if you have peace, you muſt be content with ſo much holineſs as can be had. You muſt not expect that National Churches (though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49900:8"/>you will have them <hi>Jure Divino</hi>) ſhould be as Holy, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect people of your Gathered Congregations.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am ſenſible what need we have of Diſcourſes, that are bending to one another, while ſuch Diviſions are got with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our bowels, as are like to eat our Religion quite out. One would wonder to ſee ſometimes two friends, that agree ſo well otherwiſe, as both to go to Church, both are for the ſame Liturgy, both are for the preſent King, and ready ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye than admit of Popery, and yet being rankt into a diverſe ſort of Companions under the names of <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> there is a ſecret Animoſity and Unkindneſs grows with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if no open fire of contention break out, as if they were born enemies. Do but ask one or the other, what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter between you, or what is the meaning of theſe names, <hi>Guelph</hi> and <hi>Gibeline,</hi> that divide you, they can ſay nothing, but themſelves are aſtoniſhed. There is nothing but that the <hi>Tares</hi> are ſown in mens hearts by the <hi>Evil one,</hi> while they are not aware, is the cauſe of it: And there is nothing but the love of God, and our Neighbour which is the effect of Gods ſpirit, with an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> (which muſt begin that work) like to be the cure of it. It was one of the deepeſt fetches of the Popiſh Plot, through <hi>Liberty</hi> to deſtroy <hi>Agreement:</hi> And to come to <hi>Agree</hi> now, and preſerve <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence,</hi> is the only way to be even with them.</p>
            <p>As the deſign therefore of your Papers, which is National Concord, is according to my heart deſire, and I ſhould be glad to farther it to my utmoſt: ſo muſt I take notice more particularly of one Conceſſion of yours, to wit of the Divine right of Biſhops, which others of your brethren will by no means grant. There is the <hi>Epiſcopus gregis,</hi> the Ordinary Overſeer of the flock; The <hi>Epiſcopus Praeſes,</hi> where there are ſeveral Prebyters in one Congregation; And beſides theſe you are for a <hi>Superiour ſort of ſucceſſors to the Apoſtles and Evangelists, of Divine inſtitution.</hi> Such Dioceſans that put not down Particular fixed Paſtors, or ſuch Dioceſſes as Unchurch not our Pariſhes, are not impugned by you. I am perſwaded now that the moſt of our preſent Biſhops will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49900:9"/>you, that their Dioceſſes are not Churches <hi>infimae ſpecici,</hi> but that every Parochial Congregation of Paſtor and People, are true Political Churches, and that the Miniſters Office is to <hi>Rule,</hi> as well as to <hi>Teach,</hi> though as to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of that part of their Office it is provided by the Church, that they ſhould be under the conduct of a Biſhop, as the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians provide that they be under the conduct of a <hi>Claſſis,</hi> for which there are weighty reaſons, ſo long as the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the One is but cumulative, not deſtructive to the Other. And ſo long as you will admit that the King may make ſuch a Dioceſan (like a <hi>Quorum Juſtice</hi>) to have a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice in Ordinations, there is very little for ought I ſee wanting but a Conference to reconcile you and them together.</p>
            <p>For my own part, I muſt confeſs, I am not ſo eaſie in allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Dioceſan or Metropolitan, no, nor a National Church where the King is made an Eccleſiaſtical Formal Head, any otherwiſe, than I would a Vicar-General, if it pleaſes the King, which is by <hi>Law,</hi> not by <hi>Divine inſtitution.</hi> What is more known, than that our Kings of <hi>England</hi> never were Heads of the Church, till <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eight,</hi> who was made ſo by an Act of Parliament? I like well a National Church; That the Siupream power be Head thereof; That Biſhops and Archbiſhops do ſtand (upon the Terms you here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) as Prudential, and even Neceſſary in the ſtate we are in: but not as if God had commanded it ſo, and it might be no otherwiſe. There is a diſtinction here therefore, that is needful, and you have it not. I cannot tell well how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, but <hi>Grotius,</hi> I remember, does make it in apt Terms upon ſome other Argument. It is to this ſenſe, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Divine <hi>Warrant,</hi> and a Divine <hi>Precept; a jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> as <hi>juſtum</hi> onely, or as <hi>juſſum.</hi> We may have a ſufficient warrant or ground from Scripture to do a thing, as Anolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gous to it, and yet the Scripture not command it to be done ſo as that we ſin if it be forborn upon good human reaſon. The caſe is ſo here about Epiſcopacy. There is warrant from Chriſts ſending out <hi>Twelve,</hi> and then <hi>Seventy;</hi> From Gods ſetting in his Church, <hi>Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Pastors;</hi> From
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49900:9"/>
               <hi>Paul's</hi> ſending <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> with charge over the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Creete;</hi> From the general Rules of <hi>Order, Decency, Edification;</hi> I ſay there is warrant from <hi>Scripture,</hi> upon theſe accounts, for a Superiority, and. Inferiority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Clergy, ſo as it is lawful, whereſoever it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the Publick good of the Churches of God, to ſet up Presbyterian <hi>Claſſes,</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government, placing a Dioceſan over a Paſtor, an Archbiſhop over a Dioceſan, a Vicar General over the Provinces, and the King the Head (as a Mixed perſon) over all, ſo conſtituting the National Church, or Church of <hi>England:</hi> but I cannot ſay that this is of <hi>Divine appointment.</hi> And then I pray moreover, what Head! <hi>An Eccleſiaſtical Formal Head</hi> as you ſay? No, but to ſpeak exactly, A King of a Chriſtian Kingdom is no <hi>Caput Eccleſiae qua Eccleſiae,</hi> till Conſtituted ſo; and when he is, he is not a Head <hi>Formally Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> but a Head <hi>Objective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eccleſiaſtical</hi> onely, and in that reſpect (as <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Mixt</hi> Perſon. I would grant the Biſhops to be <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino</hi> to pleaſe the Church-men) ſo far as warrantable by Scripture, upon the accounts mentioned, provided they be, as the Higher Powers judge, beſt for the Land: but (to do Juſtice to others) I deny them to be <hi>Ex praecepto Divino,</hi> ſo far as that all Nations are bound to have them, or that they may not chooſe ſome other Order of Superiority and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority, for Government, as ſerves beſt the condition of Each People. God may <hi>Allow,</hi> or approve of an Order that is made, or a thing when done, which Order he does not <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> to be made, or thing to be done.</p>
            <p>I hear lately that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have had ſeveral Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in order to a right underſtanding with one another, and that the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> are come to Terms, drawn up for a mutual Coalition. This is a good hearing, and very happy, if it may, by any means, but tend to the ſtrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way to that more Publick, and generous Concord, which ſeems the Deſign of your Sheets; that is, for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Concordant Diſſenters, and the Church-men alſo, <hi>Conformiſt</hi> and <hi>Non-conformiſt,</hi> the Chriſtians of all ſorts, that are but Tolerable, into the Unity of one Eccleſiaſtick
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49900:10"/>Political Society of the whole Nation, combined for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within it ſelf, Independent on any Forraign Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This is a Deſign worthy of your farther Study, and there is one of your brethren ready to learn more of you, that hath Offered ſomething to this Effect ſeveral years ſince, and repeated it; who concurring with you in his Endeavour for the ſetting up a National Church, and ſubmiſſion to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops upon that account, yet dare not yield to you in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Biſhops, nor National Church either, to be of Divine Inſtitution, for this reaſon; becauſe he thinks if he ſhould do ſo, he muſt deſtroy that National Union at one blow, which he and you are labouring to build. For do but ask theſe ſober Diſſenters, whether they can own a Supremacy in the King, as to Eccleſiaſtical affairs, they will grant it. Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> long ſince hath wrote, <hi>A Proteſtation of the Kings Supremacy.</hi> If you ask them then, whether we are bound to be Subject to ſuch Officers as he ſhall appoint by Law for the executing this Authority, they muſt grant it likewiſe; for if they allow the one, the other is yielded. Let us ſuppoſe now that the Biſhops, and Archbiſhops of our Land were ſuch Officers, Officers of the Church as National, made by the King for fulfilling his Charge as Head of it, and there is no Presbyterian or Independent, that I know, would or could deny ſubmiſſion to them under ſuch a Nation: But if you will impoſe upon them any Biſhop as Chriſts Officer, that is, one having a Dioceſan Government over them by his appointment, or, if you will make a National Church Governed by theſe Biſhops, to be of Divine right ſtrictly taken, there is many, and the moſt of them will reclaim pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, they cannot own any ſuch matter, and ſo this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Union, and the deſign thereof is broken. I pray there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider what you do.</p>
            <p>We muſt diſtinguiſh of what is <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> and what is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient;</hi> and of what is ſo, in regard to a Conjunction with the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or in regard to the more general Uniting into a <hi>National Church.</hi> If the Presbyterians were to come to a Compoſition with the Biſhops, and could ſay with you, My Lords! If you will challenge to your Function no more Rule
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49900:10"/>than what the Apoſtles exerciſed in the Ordinary part of their Apoſtleſhip, that is, a Superiour Directive Authority over other Paſtors in the executing their Office, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the <hi>Power</hi> it ſelf given them by Chriſt, we will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your Epiſcopacy to the <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> there is no doubt but this were a Conceſſion highly <hi>Convenient,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to this end; for I do apprehend (as I have ſaid) our preſent Biſhops are of that moderation, as they would ſtraight yield to it, and agree with them: But I muſt ſay, not <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> becauſe a ſubmiſſion alone to their Government, is enough without conceding ſo much to them; when, as to the higher End of National Concord, it is neither neceſſary, nor convenient, but inconvenient, as conducive to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding multitudes out of it, and if it be ſtood upon, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſince I wrote this, I have thought good to read over your book again, and I will ſay ſomething more, as if I were to begin afreſh, for there are Perſons of Quality and of Parts, ſeveral that favour the Diſſenters, who do entertain your Notion of a National Church, and Biſhops <hi>Jure Divino</hi> (taking your meaning in the ſtrict, not my large ſenſe before) with indignation, looking on it as a building what you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in your former books, and not with the indifferency of Spirit as I do, who look on it as an Explanation of thoſe books, whether this <hi>Jure Divino Point</hi> be right or no.</p>
            <p>Your Title is, <hi>Of National Church.</hi> A National Church may be conſidered <hi>in genere,</hi> or <hi>in ſpecie.</hi> Of a National Church <hi>in genere</hi> I will account that you have ſpoken. Of a National Church, <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> I would have you count that you are yet to ſpeak, if you can ſay any more, and I to give you the Occaſion. <hi>A National Church</hi> in genere <hi>is a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kingdom conſtituted of a Chriſtian Soveraign Magiſtrate, and of Chriſtian Subjects, Worſhipping God ordinarily in True Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Paſtoral Churches.</hi> This is the firſt Paragraph of your Book, and the Subject of your Diſcourſe, which you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; And that which you have ſaid, being not as I know by any before ſaid, and of ſuch conſequence, as it is, to be ſaid, is, I will ſay, in my Opinion, ſo Generouſly ſaid, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49900:11"/>I cannot but be pleaſed with it. A National Church, ſay you, is a <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom,</hi> Right, <hi>in genere</hi> it is ſo. A National Church therefore is of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> Right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>in genere</hi> it is ſo; There is no queſtion but God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all Nations, Kings, and People, to be Chriſtians. But we muſt proceed farther, we muſt not reſt here, but come to the conſideration of a National Church <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> and to this purpoſe there is another Definition you have elſewhere, if it be another, which is this. <hi>A Chriſtian Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Confederate Paſtoral Churches is a National Church.</hi> I cannot tell here whether you mean any more in this, than in that before, but there ſeems to me ſome farther light to have came into your mind, though perhaps you reflected not on it. For by this <hi>Confederation,</hi> you may either underſtand nothing but that Confederation, which is between the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor and Members of a Particular Church <hi>within themſelves:</hi> or a Confederation of ſuch Particular Churches <hi>with others.</hi> That is, the Confederation whereby a Particular People give up themſelves to <hi>God</hi> (which the ſeveral branches of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation that you inſtance in do but come to), and to <hi>one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to walk together under the ſame Paſtoral guidance: or the Confederation whereby diverſe Particular Paſtoral Churches, do Confederate for Union, under a Superiour Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment for their greater common good. If you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the laſt of theſe, then was you defective in what you ſaid at firſt: If you do not underſtand the laſt but the firſt onely, then are you defective as to that which ſhould come mainely into conſideration, which is the nature of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church (I ſay) <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as exiſting in the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Particular Kingdoms; unto which this Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the laſt ſenſe is not only Neceſſary but Eſſential, and to be put into the Definition thereof, as without which, there can be no rightly conſtituted, Particular National Church in the World. We looſe our labour to ſpeak of Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Churches in the Univerſal Notion, unleſs we bring the Application down to the Particular National Church in our own Land, as you know. This therefore we muſt ſtand upon.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49900:11"/>
            <p>In <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government is ſettled. In <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopal.</hi> The King is Head of both Nations. If the Head alone now were the Form of a National Church, then muſt there be but one Form of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> (I mean not one <hi>Numerical</hi> Form, which doubtleſs follows not, but one <hi>Specifical</hi> Form) becauſe the Head is but One. But, the Form of a <hi>Presbyterian National Church,</hi> and the Form of an <hi>Epiſcopal National Church</hi> are diſtinct Forms, and do diſtinguiſh and ſpecifie two Churches. The Form of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> is that Order of Superiority and Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereby the Pariſh-Churches, and Miniſters there, are ſubject to their <hi>Claſſes,</hi> and thoſe Claſſes to higher, till they come up to a <hi>National Aſſembly:</hi> The Form of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is that Order of Superiority and Subjection where by the Parochial Miniſters and their Flocks are ſubject to the <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> to the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> in regard to which, ſeveral <hi>Pariſhes</hi> do make one <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan</hi> Churches one <hi>Provincial</hi> one, and the two <hi>Provinces</hi> with the <hi>King</hi> make the <hi>Church National.</hi> This Order is the Form of theſe Churches, and the Form eſſentiates them: It is not therefore for any to think, that a Man can be a Member of either of theſe Churches, who comes not into their Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Order. A man cannot be of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Church, but he muſt ſubmit to their <hi>Presbyteries.</hi> A man cannot be of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but he muſt own <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> he muſt own it ſo far, as to ſubmit to their Government. To go to build up a National Union without this Confederation, explicit or implicit, is verily but gathering <hi>Sand</hi> for the building, and putting no <hi>Lime</hi> to it. And, this let me ſay, with all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and without offence, is that which you are doing, and can but do, by making our Biſhops and our Church (if you intend ſo) to be of Divine Inſtitution, when the generality of the Diſſenters can hereunto yield no Confederation.</p>
            <p>In your behalf therefore do I diſtinguiſh of both theſe things, of a <hi>National Church,</hi> and of <hi>Epiſcopacy, in genere &amp; in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi> In <hi>genere, in genere indefinito</hi> a National Church, in <hi>genere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definito</hi> an Epiſcopacy, are of Divine Appointment: But when we come to the conſideration of National Church <hi>in ſpecie, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49900:12"/>ſpecie definita,</hi> as they exiſt in the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, <hi>made by Men,</hi> and of Epiſcopacy <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as exiſting in our Church of <hi>England,</hi> I will ſuſpend my Belief of your ſaying ſo (the Matter being ſo apparent otherwiſe in the mention of it), ſeeing he that ſays it, does no Service really to the Church (the Biſhops that are wiſe, if they be obeyed as Eſtabliſhed by Law, caring little for that), but Diſſervice in this reſpect, that the Diſſenters, by this means, if the thing be ſtood upon, ſhall not be able to come into it: Which we muſt take heed of, as already noted, eſpecially now, when the preſent Face of things look auſpitious towards Union.</p>
            <p>There are ſome things <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome things <hi>Accidental;</hi> and there are ſome things that are the Abuſes and <hi>Corruptions</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>For the laſt of theſe, the <hi>Corruptions,</hi> there was a Paper came out (and as I apprehended, from-<hi>Lambeth</hi>) ſome few years ſince, entituled, <hi>Grievances of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>which are not in the power of the Governours of it to remedy.</hi> Two of the many I will name, <hi>One</hi> this; That the Eccleſiaſtical Power is by Law inveſted in Lay-Chancellors and Officials, who act in the name of the Biſhop and Archdeacon, when things are againſt their Wills, and they cannot help it. The <hi>other</hi> this; That a <hi>Convocation</hi> cannot take any of theſe Corruptions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to debate, to reform them without danger of a <hi>Premunire,</hi> unleſs they be firſt propoſed by the King. Under theſe Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and ſuch as theſe, does the Church her ſelf, or the Biſhops themſelves, we ſee, groan; and that for this Reaſon (which I obſerve), becauſe her Government being only what is eſtabliſhed by Law, (ſo much is he out that goes to make it of Divine Right) the Governours of it (or the Biſhops) can alter nothing, but by Act of Parliament; who yet being themſelves Members, we may well conceive they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to find a time for their own Relief; and I do more eſpecially hope, that the <hi>Reduction of Archbiſhop <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> will be taken into their conſideration upon that account.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49900:12"/>
            <p>For things <hi>Accidental</hi> to the Church, I do preſume much more on the good Temper and Reſolution of the preſent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that nothing of that kind ſhall ſtand in the way, but they will part with it for Concord. Of theſe Accidentals, ſome are of eaſier, ſome of harder departure: Of the eaſier ſort I reckon the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which I do not ſee but they may part with, and with no more Grievance, than with the Rain from off their Hats, or the Greaſe from off their Cloaths. As for the harder ſort, if the Diſſenters ſhould require of the Biſhops to forgo the Liturgy, and uſe none, this were too hard, this were a kind of thruſt at the Churches Breaſt, and She might juſtly bid a man ſtand off. If they are not againſt a Liturgy, but would have a new one compoſed in Scripture-Expreſſions, I cannot ſay but this were good, inexceptionably good, but not to be asked unleſs they ſee good; as being more than is meet, and more than needs. If it be a Reformation then only they deſire, let it be in all things which are offenſive to any ſober (not humourſome) godly perſons; this is but ſo fair, ſo honeſt, ſo fit, that the Biſhops are before hand in it, and if any are for farther Improvement, this they are for alſo.</p>
            <p>For things <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch as Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government is, it is not for any to imagin the Church ſhould part there with, for then ſhe muſt ceaſe to be the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And conſequently, unleſs a way be made out for the Diſſenters, conſcionably in ſome regard as they may, to ſubmit to that Government, there can be no Coalition into a National Church; which yet is the End both of your, and my Writing.</p>
            <p>There have been two things long on the Hearts of peaceable men, as requiſite to the Happineſs of the Kingdom, and they were foreſeen therefore and intended by His preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as one End of his <hi>Expedition into England; which was,</hi> as he tells us in his <hi>Declaration</hi> (for they are beſt expreſſed in his words) <hi>for the making ſuch Laws as may eſtabliſh a good Agreement between the Church of</hi> England <hi>and Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; as alſo, for the covering all ſuch who will live peaceably under the Government from all Perſecution upon the account of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49900:13"/>The one of theſe (called generally <hi>Indulgene</hi>) is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; the other <hi>(Comprehenſion)</hi> is yet under expectation, but no leſs needful to the Intereſt of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> than that was to the Intereſt of the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> A <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> a Church, <hi>divided</hi> ſo much <hi>againſt it ſelf</hi> as ours is, a Bleſſed Mouth hath foretold them, is not a ſafe Eſtate, and does in effect ſay to both, <hi>Look to your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is therefore hugely material, in regard to the end of theſe <hi>Sheets</hi> and to the <hi>Title,</hi> to ſpeak a little of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of that ſaid Bill which will be revived at the ſitting of this Parliament, or of another in good time, I doubt not. After a ſhort Preamble then, this Bill goes downright ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to work, (and for that reaſon it can never be too much prized) enacting, That no other Oath, Subſcription, or Declaration be required to the enjoying any Eccleſiaſtical Preferment, but the New Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy to the King and Queen, the Antipapal Teſt, the Simoniacal Oath, and one Declaration to be ſubſcribed to this ſence or purpoſe, (the words whereof being put too readily together (as ſome of them that put them will perhaps acknowledg upon reflection) I would humbly beg may be deliberately put in theſe enſuing) <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do heartily approve of the Reformation of the Church of</hi> England <hi>in her Doctrin and Worſhip, as containing all things in their kind ſufficient to Salvation: And I ſubmit to the Government thereof by Law eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill proceeds to the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> enacting the leaving off the <hi>Surplice,</hi> excepting in the <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> and leaving the <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm, and <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the Sacrament to the liberty of the <hi>Parent</hi> and <hi>Receiver,</hi> with ſome the like things, I think but have forgot, that have no Rubin them. Only the great difficulty lying bout <hi>Orders,</hi> I cannot but, upon Examination of other Expedients, give my full Conſent to the Motion of the Biſhops themſelves, as to this caſe, provided they be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the words wherein they expreſs it, which I beg again may be thus:</p>
            <p>Be it farther enacted, That thoſe Miniſters who have been ordained ſince the Firſt of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year 1660, by Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters only, ſhall receive a ſecond Impoſition of Hands by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49900:13"/>in this form. <hi>For thy Reception, as a Miniſter in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and thy holding and exerciſing that Office to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Conſcience of others as well as thy own; If thou beeſt not Ordained already, be thou Ordained; If thou beeſt, be thou Confirmed, by the Impoſition of my Hands, to the Glory of God, and Edification of the Church, in the place where thou art, or ſhalt be called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words <hi>[If thou beeſt not Ordained already]</hi> do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a doubt. The Miniſter himſelf Ordained by Presbyters (I will ſuppoſe) doubts not in the leaſt of the Validity of his orders by them, and he cannot ſubmit to theſe words (if they were put alone) in regard to his <hi>own</hi> Conſcience: But, foraſmuch as the Biſhop perhaps, or others with whom he is concerned, may doubt of it, theſe words (as thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned) may be ſpoken <hi>bona fide,</hi> in regard to <hi>theirs,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Lye, Diſſembling or Equivocation. Neither is there any Adjuſtment that can atone both ſides, beſides this; for, the Miniſter ordained before receives no diminution to his Miniſtry hereby, ſeeing he yields to no more than this, and the Unſatisfied with his Miniſtry already can be ſatisfied with no leſs than this. If the Biſhop ſhould only <hi>Admit</hi> a man to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of his Miniſtry in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Spiritual Power</hi> received already <hi>acknowledged;</hi> this indeed would ſerve the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> but not the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>thoſe</hi> that <hi>doubt</hi> it. If any thing be done that implies the denial of the <hi>Power,</hi> it is againſt the Conſcience of the Miniſter, but when the Power is not <hi>Denyed</hi> nor <hi>Granted,</hi> neither are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but both accommodated as much as need be, and that is enough. If the man be ſhocked at ſuch a Suppoſition <hi>[If thou beeſt not Ordained]</hi> he muſt be ſet right again at thoſe words that follow, <hi>[If thou beeſt, be thou confirmed]</hi> and conſequently, in regard there are really in many places ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral truly pious People, that believe a man no Miniſter unleſs Ordained by a Biſhop, and ſo ſcruples his baptizing their Children, and the receiving the Sacrament of him, the <hi>Nonconformiſt Miniſter</hi> that ſhall be comprehended by this <hi>Act,</hi> will be bound, in point of Conſcience, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch as may be of his Pariſh, <hi>(Conſcience I ſay, not thy own, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49900:14"/>of the others)</hi> to the yielding to any the like thing as this (which is not ſinful) that his Miniſtry may <hi>run and be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and receive no Obſtruction upon that account.</p>
            <p>At the end of the Bill there was a Clauſe for appointing ſome Biſhops and Doctors of the Church to that healing work, for which the King after gave a Commiſſion; and in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of the ſame therefore, I would beg laſtly, that this Clauſe may be put as near as may be, into theſe words following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And, Foraſmuch as the Excellent Government of the Church by Biſhops, as it was Reformed and Eſtabliſhed in</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth and Q.</hi> Elizabeths <hi>days, is to be ſtill upheld, and ſeveral things in regard to the Books of the Liturgy, and Ordering Prieſts and Deacons, and the Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions; and in regard to the Exerciſe of Diſcipline, and otherwiſe, do require Redreſs, Reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Improvement: In order whereunto it pleaſed the King to grant a Commiſſion to certain Biſhops and Doctors of the Church, who have made ſome progreſs therein: Be it enacted,—That theſe Commiſſioners ſhall be hereby authorized to call or convene half a dozen of the grave and moderate Nonconformiſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who, upon conſultation with their Brethren, ſhall peruſe what theſe Commiſſioners have prepared, and offer to the ſaid Commiſſioners in Writing whatſoever they deſire farther, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Concord, and when theſe Commiſſioners have conſidered thereof, and perfected the whole, as themſelves ſee meet, they ſhall preſent it to His Majesty, to be communicated to a Convocation or Parliament, when and how it ſhall ſeem beſt to his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two ſorts, according to His Majeſty's Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before mentioned, of Proteſtant Diſſenters; <hi>One</hi> that own the eſtabliſhed Miniſtry, the Liturgy, and our Pariſh-Churches: The <hi>Other</hi> that do not, or cannot own them. For thoſe that <hi>cannot,</hi> they cannot be <hi>comprehended,</hi> and their Caſe being conſidered, they have <hi>Liberty</hi> granted; they muſt not be knock'd on the Head. For thoſe that <hi>can,</hi> their Caſe is to be conſidered likewiſe, and if this Bill without altering any more than thus (Tho' if any man would know <hi>all things</hi> to perfect it, he may find <hi>them</hi> in one, drawn purpoſely up, in that little Book called <hi>The Samaritan</hi>) be brought into the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49900:14"/>Houſe; ſo that it paſs with the Grant but of thoſe few things which are contain'd in it, together with impowering the aforeſaid Commiſſioners unto this farther buſineſs for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of more, there is ſo much obtained herein, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly conducive to this end of <hi>Comprehenſion;</hi> which would be, I count, a bleſſed Ground for preſent Peace, as a happy ſort of <hi>Interim,</hi> till time brought forth ſomething farther to perfection. But both theſe <hi>Acts,</hi> that for <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and this for <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> (if the laſt come alſo into an <hi>Act</hi>) are yet but <hi>Scaffolds</hi> (tho' ſo much needful) in order to this greater Works, the building up ſuch a Church, as may be capacious both of the <hi>Indulged</hi> and <hi>Comprehended,</hi> to live together with the Church-men as fellow-Members of the ſame Society Political in the enjoyment of the common Peace and Religion of Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo <hi>God may be one, and his Name one,</hi> throughout the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I will add ſuch a Church, as being compacted within its ſelf, and ſtrenghtened with ſuch a Union, it may be the Glory of our <hi>Friends,</hi> and <hi>Impregnable</hi> againſt our <hi>Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to this effect in the Reign of the <hi>preſent</hi> King, which was but ſpoken of, and feared, under the <hi>laſt,</hi> would indeed do our buſineſs. If there be any Proteſtant Lawyer ſo deliberate and wiſe, as to be able to digeſt ſo great a matter, he may do well to read Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s <hi>Politica,</hi> who, in one Chapter of the <hi>Extent of a Particular Church,</hi> goes to prove how eaſily the Multitude of Chriſtians in one Nation aſſociated and ſubjected to one Supreme Judicatory, may be ordered, even as a ſingle Independent Congregation may; and he hath many clear things upon it, as a man of excelling Skill in that ſtudy.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am ſenſible how much the publick, and how little your own private Advantage does concern you, and therefore I humbly conjure you, and beſeech you, to take this matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſecond thoughts, becauſe it is one and the ſame thing as to the main, muſt be thought over, and beat upon, to bring any matter to the maturity of doing good; and, the Lord knows whether there be, or be not, any ſuch kind of Good in the Womb of Providence for this Land. There was a Sheet, or Half-ſheet came out a good many years ago under the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49900:15"/>of <hi>Materials for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which were reviſed and put out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain more lately under the Title of <hi>A Draught</hi> for <hi>Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation;</hi> that is, National Union, National Accommodation. If you have read it already, it is ſo much the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then your Thoughts will be the more prepared to do what I deſire of you; that is, to read over the ſame again with ſome deeper Animadverſion, not barely to confute it, or ſome things in it, which is a little Work any other body can do, but to take it into conſideration, ſo as to examin what is well as what is amiſs, to approve as to diſprove, to add what is wanting as to lop what is unfit; that is, to read it over, not for <hi>destroying</hi> but <hi>edifying;</hi> or to look it over, as you would the Trees in your Garden, to pluck off the <hi>Snails,</hi> but to cheriſh the <hi>Budds,</hi> becauſe there is, or there may be for ought you know, a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> in them. I do think fit to write this Letter on purpoſe that I may ſend with it the Paper mentioned, look'd again over, and improved, to that end. And I pray God to direct your Thoughts and Labours ſtill, that you may ſo <hi>prove all things,</hi> as to <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Draught.</head>
            <p>WHereas there are ſeveral Parties of Chriſtians in the Nation, who muſt and will ever differ in their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions about the Church and Diſcipline of it in the Queſtion which is of Chriſt's Inſtitution, it is not our Diſputes about the Church as particular (which are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be mutually forborn, and every party left herein to their own Perſwaſion) but a common Agreement in what we can agree, and that is in the Church as National, muſt heal our Breaches.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49900:15"/>
            <p>The Catholicks are for one Univerſal Organical Church throughout the World, whereof the Pope is Head, according to ſome, and the Biſhops conven'd in a General Council, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to others.</p>
            <p>That there is a Catholick Church viſible on Earth, as well as inviſible, whereof Chriſt is Head, who was on Earth, and is now viſible in Heaven, is received alſo by Proteſtants: But, that this Church is <hi>per integrum Organical,</hi> and under the Government either of a <hi>Monarchy</hi> by the Pope, or of an <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracy</hi> by a <hi>General Council,</hi> it ſeems a thing not poſſible in Nature, becauſe neither can an <hi>Oecumenical Council</hi> ever be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor any <hi>one</hi> man be ſufficient to take on him the Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Political Church is a Community of Chriſtians brought into an Order of Superiority and Inferiority, by an Head and Members organiz'd for the Exerciſe of that Government which is proper to it: But the whole Earth is not capable of any ſuch Order: And Councils therefore which are gathered out of ſeveral Countries, or of Biſhops belonging to more Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions than of one Supreme Power, may be had for mutual. Advice and <hi>Concord,</hi> but not for <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Nation, Empire, or Kingdom which conſiſts of one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate and People, who are generally Chriſtians, are capable of ſuch an Eccleſiaſtical Polity, and a National Church Political in <hi>England</hi> is to be aſſerted and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church of England</hi> then is a Political Society of all the Chriſtians (Conforming or Tolerated) in the Land, united in the King as Head, and organized by the Biſhops, for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thoſe Laws or Government which he chuſes for their Spiritual Good and Publick Peace.</p>
            <p>There is this difference between a Church <hi>National,</hi> the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> and <hi>Particular</hi> Churches: The two latter are of <hi>Divine Right</hi> and <hi>Eſſential</hi> Conſideration, but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is of <hi>Human Institution;</hi> for, it is manifeſtly <hi>Accidental</hi> to the Church of Chriſt, that the whole People ſhould be <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49900:16"/>
            <p>Not but it is the duty of all Nations, Kings and People to become Chriſtians, <hi>Go and teach all Nations Baptizing them,</hi> and that Chriſtian Kingdoms therefore as they conſiſt of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that do meet in Particular Congregations for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the True God, and Jeſus Chriſt, and do exerciſe that Government, which the Paſtor hath over his flock, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Office from Chriſt, and no other than that, are of <hi>Divine appointment:</hi> But the Combination of theſe Churches, or the Paſtors thereof in an Order of Superiority, and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority for the Exerciſe of a Regiment, that is National o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the whole body of the Kingdom, by ſetting Biſhop in a Dioceſs, and an Archbiſhop in a Province, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding no farther as to a Patriarchat and General Council, but making a ſtop here, and Conſtituting the Nation thereby one Governing Church independent on any other from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board; this appears of no <hi>Divine,</hi> or <hi>Canonical</hi> Right, but muſt derive its Authority from an <hi>Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſtinguiſh we here of the Government of the Church, as <hi>Internal</hi> belonging to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>External</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to <hi>Men:</hi> And of the <hi>External</hi> Regiment thereof, which is either <hi>Formal</hi> belonging to the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or Officers of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or <hi>Objective,</hi> belonging to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſo call'd becauſe the matters of the Church in this reſpect, are the Object of his Civil Power: Whether the Community now of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in <hi>England</hi> may be united into a National Church under a pure Formal Government, we leave to others to diſpute that will. But that the main Body of the Nation are, or may be conſtituted a proper Political Church National, under that Mix'd Regiment, which is both Formal and Objective, and ſo exerciſed by the Biſhops, as the proper Organs thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King (with Authority as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as <hi>Miniſters</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Force), is what we hold indiſputable, and would lay as a Foundation-ſtone of Peace in the Matter of Religion, between all Perſons in the Kingdom capable of it.</p>
            <p>The Government of this Church is by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and if their Authority be not received and owned, ſo far as that the generality of the Nation, the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> as well as others,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49900:16"/>yield to it, there can be no Union. Now, when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Land</hi> is a <hi>Mixt</hi> Government, as Politicians tell us on another account, why may not the Government of the <hi>Church</hi> be <hi>Mixt</hi> too upon this account, to wit, in that, as the <hi>King</hi> muſt be a <hi>Mixed Perſon</hi> to be <hi>Head,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> muſt be <hi>Mixt Perſons</hi> too to be his <hi>Officers;</hi> Mixt Perſons in regard to the exerciſe of both this <hi>Objective</hi> and <hi>Formal</hi> Regiment, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving the one from the <hi>King,</hi> as <hi>over</hi> other Miniſters, and the other from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Fellows</hi> with them; that ſo thoſe that ſcruple their Submiſſion to them upon <hi>one</hi> account, may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied upon <hi>another:</hi> which by and by will be explained.</p>
            <p>Let the Parliament therefore we have, or any other, be heartily for the Publick Good and Thriving of <hi>England,</hi> which muſt be by an entire Liberty of Conſcience in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the narrow Spirit of any ſingle Party or Faction, and when ſuch a Parliament ſhall ſit about the Buſineſs of Union to purpoſe, the Bill ſhould be brought in, entituled, <hi>An Act for declaring the Conſtitution of our Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>A Parliament is the Repreſentative of the whole Nation, and no doubt but by Conſent and Agreement they might (upon the account mentioned) <hi>Make</hi> a new Conſtitution, and much more may they <hi>Declare</hi> the Conſtitution of it.</p>
            <p>It ſhould be declared then, in ſuch a Bill or Act, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> conſiſts of the King as the Head, or <hi>Pars imperans,</hi> who (in his <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Capacity, as <hi>incorporated</hi> with his <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi>) is to give <hi>Laws</hi> thereto, and all the ſeveral Aſſemblies of Chriſtians which he ſhall tolerate, as the <hi>pars ſubdita,</hi> or Body.</p>
            <p>Some Diſcrimination between the <hi>Tolerable</hi> and <hi>Intolerable,</hi> is indeed never to be gainſaid by any wiſe and good man, unto whom there is no Liberty can be deſireable, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with theſe three things, the <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Creed,</hi> a <hi>Good Life,</hi> and the Fundamental <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not for any private Perſons, but a Parliament, with a Convocation, to preſcribe the Terms of National Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but we would have all our Aſſemblies that are tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be declared Legal by ſuch an Act, and thereby Parts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49900:17"/>of the National Church, as well as the Parochial Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The Church here therefore muſt come under a double con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, as the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and as the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Take the Church as the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and there muſt be (as we have ſaid at firſt) endleſs Controverſy about this point, who are the true Members of it (and who the Officers, whether Biſhops or no): But take it under the Conſideration as <hi>National,</hi> and there will be none at all, for thoſe muſt be Members (and thoſe Officers) whom the Head by a Law does allow to be parts of the Body, and the King under this Notion only is made Head of the Church by the <hi>Statute,</hi> that is, as it called <hi>Eccleſia Anglicana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of all ſorts (not excepting the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks) as well as <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> will acknowledge the King to be Supream Coercive Governour over all Perſons, and in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, throughout his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and will not ſtand out perhaps if more be required. Again, the Diſſenters of all ſorts even the Congregationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts of very Sect, are ready to ſubmit to any Power Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally derived from the King, and upon ſuch an account will admit of a Superintendency of the Biſhops, as Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Magiſtrates under him, when they cannot own any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that they have over other Miniſters, from Jeſus Chriſt; and will not Papiſts alſo be Subject to all Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is exerciſed Legally in his Name, howſoever they may queſtion the Spiritual Title of the Engliſh Clergy, and their Succeſſion?</p>
            <p>We would have Biſhops then (<hi>qua Biſhops</hi> as diſtinct in <hi>Office</hi> from <hi>Prieſts</hi>) declared no other by <hi>Law</hi> than the <hi>Kings</hi> Officers, whoſe Power is but <hi>Objectively</hi> Eccleſiaſtical, and to Act <hi>Circa ſacra</hi> onely, by vertue of his Authority, whether they have any Authority elſe from the <hi>Goſpel</hi> than ſo, ſo long as they have this by <hi>Law,</hi> it need not at all be toucht.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49900:17"/>
            <p>As <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> did commit the charge incumbent upon him, as Supream Magiſtrate, in regard to all <hi>Matters of the Lord,</hi> unto the care of <hi>Amariah</hi> being <hi>Chief Prieſt,</hi> and in regard to the <hi>Kings Matters</hi> unto <hi>Zebadiah,</hi> being as the <hi>Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> of the Realm: So ſhould the Dioceſan Biſhop be in our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> as the Judges are in <hi>Civil</hi> matters, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes altogether of his Majeſty, and execute his Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a State-Point, which was throughly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſed by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eight,</hi> whoſe Divines did agree on two Orders alone <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Deacon,</hi> to be of <hi>Divine</hi> Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that the Superiority of a Biſhop over a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or of one Biſhop over another, was but by the <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Laws of Men onely, as appears in that Authentick book then put out, entitituled, <hi>The Neceſſary Erudition:</hi> And conſequently, that the Biſhop could not have, or Exert any Juriſdiction over the Subject unleſs warranted, and derived from the King, without danger of a <hi>Premunire;</hi> which made <hi>Bonner</hi> (with others) hold his Biſhoprick by <hi>Commiſſion. Ambo tenent unum eundem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Ordinem,</hi> ſay <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s <hi>Canons</hi> in <hi>Lambard's Saxon Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this ground, if it ſhould pleaſe his Majeſty to Chuſe ſome Perſons of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to this Office, Authorizing them to it no otherwiſe, than by a like <hi>Commiſſion</hi> (which they ſhould alſo hold, with the Judges, <hi>Quam diu ſe bene geſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint):</hi> As none of them could ſcruple then the acceptance, ſo muſt a Union from that day forward Commence in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are ſenſible unto what diſtreſs, the Miniſters of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation of all ſorts may be brought in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Diſcipline over ſome Potent, Turbulent and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory Members; and what relief he might find in ſuch an External Eccleſiaſtical Officer as this: We are ſenſible how many inconveniences of Congregational Epiſcopacy, may by this means onely, be ſalved.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49900:18"/>
            <p>Their work in general ſhould be, to ſuperviſe the Churches of all parties in their Dioceſſes, that they walk according to their own Principles, in due order, agreeable to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the Peace of one another; whether in the Aſſemblies of the Brethren, or Synods of their Paſtors for Mutual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. And more particularly in the obſervance of all Laws and Limitations, Rules or Canons, which the King as Supreme Head ſhall by advice of a Convocation, and the Conſent of his three Eſtates in Parliament, make on purpoſe (as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt work to be conſidered), and impoſe upon them all, with reſpect both to the publick Emolument, and the ſafety of his own Perſon. Dignity, and Dominions.</p>
            <p>For example: Suppoſe this to be one Canon or Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, That no <hi>Young,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>Grave</hi> men only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Sects,</hi> be admitted to be <hi>Teachers. Not a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, lest he fall into the condemnation of the Devil.</hi> Another this: That all <hi>Conventicles</hi> be kept open, as the <hi>Churches</hi> are, for any to come and hear that will, that no Sedition be there hatched or broached. <hi>If all prophecy, and there come in one that believeth not, he is convinced of all, he is judged of all, and the Secrets of his Heart being made manifeſt, he will fall down and worſhip, and report, that God is with you of a Truth.</hi> Another this: That when there is occaſion for the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Miniſters of ſeveral Churches for Conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any weighty Affair among the Tolerated and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brethren, the Biſhop ſhall have cognizance of the Cauſe, to authorize the Meeting. <hi>For this cauſe test I thee at</hi> Creete, <hi>that thou ſhouldſt ſet in order the things that are wanting.</hi> Another, in regard to the Conformiſts, this, That Biſhop and Miniſters ſhall reſide alwaies where their Flock is, unleſs upon unavoidable occaſions. <hi>And ſay to</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus, <hi>Take heed to the Miniſtry which thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.</hi> One more, this: That whereas no man can be an Allowed or Licenſed Preacher, but he muſt ſubſcribe the <hi>Articles of the Church,</hi> and thoſe that do ſubſcribe ordinarily, are men of diverſe Judgments ſuch as <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> who cannot, and do not, ſubſcribe both of them in the ſame ſenſe:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49900:18"/>It ſhould be declared in a Canon, as allowed by the Church That theſe Articles are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed only in a<note n="*">
                  <hi>Interpretatio eſt triplex, Authentica, quae fit authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate illius, qui poteſt legem condere: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſualis, quae fit conſuetudine: Doctrinalis, quae fit per doctrinam, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate interpetrum.</hi> Suar. De Legibus, l. 6. c. 1. There are many conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly learned, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſcrutinous into ſome points, more than others, they cannot ſubſcribe them ſo eaſie as others, and this would be a great Relief both to the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> of that ſort, and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> in regard to this one thing which ſtill pinches in the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>Liberty.</hi> The truth is, all Impoſitions are to be taken in the Sence of the Impoſers, and when that Sence which was intended by the Convocation that compiled theſe Articles, is the only true, genuine, authentick Senſe or Meaning of them, there is no man, in good earneſt, that is called to ſubſcribe the Articles, but he is ſeriouſly to confider what he judges in his Conſcience to have been <hi>Their</hi> Meaning, and if he can ſubſcribe them in that Sence, he is to do it, if he cannot, he is to forbear. This being ſo hard a Chapter it is fit the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould put in, and declare, that that Sence whereof a man can hardly be ſure even ſo far as to act in Faith, is not the Sence <hi>she</hi> impoſes; but that any other may ſuffice, which in a literal Conſtruction can be made good, whether of the Subſcriber's own, or of any Judicious Expoſitor.</note> 
               <hi>Doctrinal,</hi> not the <hi>Authentick</hi> Interpretation. <hi>Let every one be fully perſwaded in his own mind.</hi> I mention theſe 4 or 5 things inſtead of many, to be the Canonical Matter of ſuch Impoſitions, as may be found fit to be laid, ſome on all, ſome on ſome Perſons, not needful for others; and it is <hi>Time,</hi> and the <hi>Trial,</hi> and <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> which muſt be the Mother to bring them forth, and cultivate them after, to their beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>To the making ſuch Canons we humbly motion a third <hi>Clerk</hi> for the <hi>Convocation,</hi> to be added to the two in every Dioceſs, and choſe out of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> with indifferent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all ſorts of them, that mutual Satisfaction and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord may thereby be proſecuted with Unanimity of Heart and Good-will through all the Churches: And the two Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York</hi> ſhould unite in this Convocation for the making them one <hi>National Church,</hi> and not two <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial</hi> ones, in a diverſe Aſſembly. The continuance of two Provinces with a ſeparate Government in either, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with one National Political Society, and keeps the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49900:19"/>Saddle on both, for the French Popery at leaſt, if not the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> to get up again upon us.</p>
            <p>If a temporary Vicar-General were made by the King eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Convocation, by whoſe Authority, delegated to him over both Provinces to that purpoſe, the Members of both were to be convened; and if when any buſineſs of moment were on the Anvil, no man but one, herein truly noble, as excelling others in Learning and Virtue, (ſuch a one as Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>), might be choſen, by whoſe Conduct and Moderation things might be carried better than they have ſometimes been: Who does not ſee, but this might be for advantage to the Affairs of Religion? The Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had not done ſo well as it did, had not <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſuperviſed them.</p>
            <p>Government conſiſts in Legiſlation and Judgment. The Supreme Power of this Kingdom, as to the exerciſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, lies not (We know) in the King alone, but in the King and his Parliament. The whole <hi>Body</hi> of the Nation are to be accounted in their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> to meet the <hi>Head,</hi> and the Laws to be made by the <hi>Whole,</hi> whereby our Birthright of being a <hi>Free State</hi> or Free People is maintained. The Abſolute Supreme Power therefore of this <hi>Kingdom of England</hi> muſt lye in King, Lords, and Commons, as unified in a Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the Houſe of Lords as virtually ſo unified is the Higheſt Judicatory. As for the Supreme Power then of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> the Power of making Canons, and of judging in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes as to the laſt Appeal, it does in like manner not lye in the Biſhops only, but in the <hi>King</hi> thus incorporated, and a <hi>Convocation.</hi> Every Pariſh-Church in the Land is to be accounted by its Paſtor to chuſe its Repreſentative in this Convocation. Every particular Church which is tolerated, or ſhall be tolerated by Law, is thereby made part of the National, and muſt therefore have the ſame Right with the Parochial Congregations. Let thus much be declared, and upon this Foundation (whereof of Firſt-ſtone was laid before) will this great Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we do go about to build, be reared, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragably upheld. For, if the Perſons that repreſent their Churches are united in one <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> then muſt thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49900:19"/>Churches that are repreſented be ſuppoſed as united in one <hi>Body.</hi> It is, as Members of one National Society that they chuſe their Repreſentatives for the making up this <hi>Convocation,</hi> which is the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> If we look into our Antiquaries, and old Hiſtorians, we ſhall find, That before the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> (at leaſt under the <hi>Saxons</hi>) our Parliaments and Clergy were ſtill one Aſſembly, and no Canons made, but by both together, Which ancient uſage manifeſtly powers the nature of a <hi>Parliament</hi> to be the meaſure of a <hi>Convocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me add, as to this Supreme Power of the Keys men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, That the Subject thereof is the whole Church, as we ſhall find it proved by our Divines, ſuch as Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> againſt the Papiſts, from that only place for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> (Other Texts ſpeak (ſay they) of the Keys of <hi>Doctrin</hi>), <hi>Tell the Church;</hi> that is, a <hi>Particular</hi> Church, which a National Church (unleſs diſtinguiſhed) is, for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Church cannot be <hi>told.</hi> Now, the <hi>King</hi> being one, and the chief one in the Church as National, and the Power ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>whole, He,</hi> (he in his Vicar) together with the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> repreſenting the whole, muſt have this Power reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him with them: Although, as the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> lies in the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> with the <hi>King,</hi> yet the <hi>Executive</hi> Power lies in him only; ſo the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power of the Church lies in him with the <hi>Convocation,</hi> yet the <hi>Executive</hi> in the <hi>Biſhops</hi> only. No Church-Execution by the Sword-bearer, but they Key-bearer; and no Penalty by Canon, but Rebuke and Excommunication.</p>
            <p>To return; By this means ſhall one Organ more be added to this great Political Society, for deriving an Influence from the Head to theſe Parts of the Body as well as others, which now ſeem neglected, and to have no care taken of them.</p>
            <p>The grand and more eſpecial Buſineſs of ſuch an equally-modell'd Convocation, ſhould be the reviſing the Book of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons for the reverſing the main Body of them, having been fitted to that narrow Scantling, which is unworthy the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and for the leaving only thoſe, and making new, (as we have exemplified in ſome for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49900:20"/>inſtance-ſake before) which do, or will be made to ſuit to that larger Conſtitution thereof, intended by this Paper.</p>
            <p>And having ſaid now thus much for Explanation of this Deſign, we muſt ſay ſome little alſo in favour of it.</p>
            <p>The Deſign of ſuch a National Accommodation as this, ſhall <hi>advance,</hi> not <hi>leſſen</hi> the outward Power and Honour of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> extending it over thoſe who before had no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Regard for their Function; while yet it would caſe them of the tremendous Burthen of ſuch a <hi>Cura ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum</hi> they take on them otherwiſe, as muſt be of impoſſible performance.</p>
            <p>This Deſign (which is ſuppoſed to find us in our Diviſions, and not to make any) ſhall by little and little (with God's Bleſſing on it) cool Animoſities, and enkindle Charity and Holineſs among all Parties, which now is ſo much wanting, while thoſe that are <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and much more thoſe that are <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> do agree in the Subſtance of one Chriſtianity, having the ſame Scriptures, the ſame Articles of Faith in the three Creeds, and the ſame Rule of Manners in the Decalogue. <hi>There is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</hi> They cannot indeed have all Communion in the ſame External Worſhip, but they can have it in the Internal Adoration of the ſame Bleſſed Trinity, and in one Hope of our calling unto Eternal Life, through Chriſt Jeſus. They muſt ſeparate into ſeveral Congregations, but there ſhall be no <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Body</hi> by this means, for all that.</p>
            <p>For, as while the Supreme Power allowed only Parochial Meetings, as eſtabliſhed by Law, it hath been accounted Schiſm to go to ſeparate Aſſemblies: So the Scene being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and theſe <hi>ſeparate</hi> Congregations alſo made <hi>Legal,</hi> this <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or Mens being called <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> in that Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, muſt vaniſh, and be at an end. Indeed, theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Congregations will accuſe one another as guilty of Sin and Schiſm before God, for each ſeparating from the others Communion, and threaten <hi>His</hi> Judgment: But ſo long as there is no ſeparating from the <hi>Church</hi> whereof
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49900:20"/>the King is <hi>Head,</hi> while he tolerates the Meetings of both, and makes them Parts of it as National, there ſhall be no Proſecution of Law againſt any, but all quiet, as Fellow-Members upon that account.</p>
            <p>Only, as to the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> (as they call themſelves) we muſt conſider, there are many of them that have received ſuch Principles, as that they cannot ſwear to the Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the King, and ſo are uncapable of this National Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with others (it being an inconſiſtent thing to diſown the <hi>Head,</hi> and yet be of the <hi>Body</hi>) and theſe are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted therefore as <hi>without,</hi> that is, <hi>out of the Church,</hi> who yet (as the <hi>Jews</hi> do) may <hi>live</hi> in the <hi>Land:</hi> And there are many, it is like, that can ſwear to the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy (it being rational to think they may do that now, which in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight's Reign they one did) and will ſubmit too to every thing elſe required to the rendring them <hi>tolerable,</hi> and theſe are to be dealt with as <hi>within,</hi> who yet are not to imagin for all that, that a Proteſtant King and Parliament ſhould allow of their <hi>Mafs</hi> in Publick, as they do the <hi>Service-Book.</hi> This were not to <hi>tolerate</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but to <hi>ſet up Popery;</hi> whereas the determining what is to be permitted to one Party, and what to another, ſo as no Detriment may be brought to the Church or State, and no Sin or Guilt upon the Nation by that Permiſſion, is a nicer thing, and requires the weighty Debate of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> (if not more than one) before it be handed to a Parliament.</p>
            <p>There is one Motion farther ſhould be added, and that is for another Bill alſo to be brought in for the preventing, and taking away two things, which are the Peſts of the Conforming Clergy; the one is <hi>Simony,</hi> and to be done ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually by the impoſing only the Simoniacal Oath on the <hi>Patrons</hi> of all Benefices, as well as on the <hi>Incumbents.</hi> The other is <hi>Pluralities,</hi> we mean both of <hi>Livings</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi> impartially, to this end, that the King may have where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal to engage thoſe he receives into the Church thus enlarged, and conſequently reſtores to their Labours by this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49900:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Accommodation, for that is a thing will make the Favour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſignificant to ſuch perſons.</p>
            <p>We will conclude with one Argument for what we have propoſed. There is no Power given upon Earth for any man to command that which he in his Conſcience does judge to be Sin: <hi>Non datur poteſt as ad malum.</hi> But to <hi>Conform</hi> in all things to the preſent Church according to Law, is Sin in the Judgment of <hi>Diſſenters, Catholicks,</hi> and others, and the late King was a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> of one ſort himſelf. The King therefore that was ſo lately, could not really put the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks upon Conformity, and if he would appear equal to all People, he could not put any other Diſſenters on it neither, for the ſame cauſe. That which the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, was both in his Conſcience and in theirs, a thing prohibited of God. He could not therefore put the Laws in execution being againſt God. And if he could not do it acting only but as an honeſt man, that abides by his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, we have no reaſon to apprehend, that the King and Queen we have now ſhould be ever brought to do it, maugre all the Enticements of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or Frowns of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
